<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<book>
  <title>Veusz - a scientific plotting package</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Jeremy</firstname>

      <surname>Sanders</surname>

      <email>jeremy@jeremysanders.net</email>
    </author>

    <copyright>
      <year>2013</year>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>
	This document is licensed under the GNU General Public
	License, version 2 or greater. Please see the file COPYING for
	details, or see <ulink
	url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.html" />.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
      <title>Veusz</title>

      <para>Veusz is a scientific plotting package. It was designed to
      be easy to use, easily extensible, but powerful. The program
      features a graphical user interface, which works under
      Unix/Linux, Windows or Mac OS X. It can also be easily scripted
      (the saved file formats are similar to Python scripts) or used
      as module inside Python. Veusz reads data from a number of
      different types of data file, it can be manually entered, or
      constructed from other datasets.</para>

      <para>In Veusz the document is built in an object-oriented
      fashion, where a document is built up by a number of widgets in
      a hierarchy. For example, multiple function or xy widgets can be
      placed inside a graph widget, and many graphs can be placed in a
      grid widget.</para>

      <para>The technologies behind Veusz include PyQt (a very easy to
      use Python interface to Qt, which is used for rendering and the
      graphical user interface, GUI) and numpy (a package for Python
      which makes the handling of large datasets easy). Veusz can be
      extended by the user easily by adding plugins. Support for
      different data file types can be added with import
      plugins. Dataset plugins automate the manipulation of
      datasets. Tools plugins automate the manipulation of the
      document.</para>
   </section>

    <section>
      <title>Terminology</title>
      <para>Here we define some terminology for future use.</para>

      <section>
	<title>Widget</title>
	<para>A document and its graphs are built up from widgets.
	These widgets can often by placed within each other, depending
	on the type of the widget. A widget has children (those
	widgets placed within it) and its parent. The widgets have a
	number of different settings which modify their
	behaviour. These settings are divided into properties, which
	affect what is plotted and how it is plotted. These would
	include the dataset being plotted or whether an axis is
	logarithmic.  There are also formatting settings, including
	the font to be used and the line thickness. In addition they
	have actions, which perform some sort of activity on the
	widget or its children, like "fit" for a fit widget.</para>

	<para>As an aside, using the scripting interface, widgets are
	specified with a "path", like a file in Unix or Windows. These
	can be relative to the current widget (do not start with a
	slash), or absolute (do not start with a slash). Examples of
	paths include, "/page1/graph1/x", "x" and ".".</para>

	<para>The widget types include</para>

	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><command>document</command> - representing a
	      complete document. A document can contain pages. In
	      addition it contains a setting giving the page size for
	      the document.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><command>page</command> - representing a page in a
	      document. One or more graphs can be placed on a page, or
	      a grid.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><command>graph</command> - defining an actual
	      graph. A graph can be placed on a page or within a
	      grid. Contained within the graph are its axes and
	      plotters. A graph can be given a background fill and a
	      border if required. It also has a margin, which
	      specifies how far away from the edge of its parent widget
	      to plot the body of the graph.</para>

	    <para>A graph can contain several axes, at any position
	      on the plot. In addition a graph can use axes defined in
	      parent widgets, shared with other graphs.</para>

	    <para>More than one graph can be placed within in a
	      page. The margins can be adjusted so that they lie
	      within or besides each other.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><command>grid</command> - containing one or more
	    graphs. A grid plots graphs in a gridlike fashion. You can
	    specify the number of rows and columns, and the plots are
	    automatically replotted in the chosen arrangement. A grid
	    can contain graphs or axes. If an axis is placed in a
	    grid, it can be shared by the graphs in the grid.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><command>axis</command> - giving the scale for
	    plotting data. An axis translates the coordinates of the
	    data to the screen. An axis can be linear or logarithmic,
	    it can have fixed endpoints, or can automatically get them
	    from the plotted data. It also has settings for the axis
	    labels and lines, tick labels, and major and minor tick
	    marks.</para>

	    <para>An axis may be "horizontal" or "vertical" and can
	    appear anywhere on its parent graph or grid.</para>

	    <para>If an axis appears within a grid, then it can be
	    shared by all the graphs which are contained within the
	    grid.</para>

	    <para> The <command>axis-broken</command> widget is an
	    axis sub-type. It is an axis type where there are
	    jumps in the scale of the axis.</para>

	    <para>The <command>axis-function</command> widget allows
	    the user to create an axis where the values are scaled by
	    a monotonic function, allowing non-linear and
	    non-logarithmic axis scales. The widget can also be linked
	    to a different axis via the function.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>plotters - types of widgets which plot data or add
	      other things on a graph. There is no actual plotter
	      widget which can be added, but several types of plotters
	      listed below. Plotters typically take an axis as a
	      setting, which is the axis used to plot the data on the
	      graph (default x and y).</para>

	    <orderedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para><command>function</command> - a plotter which
		  plots a function on the graph. Functions can be
		  functions of x or y (parametric functions are not
		  done yet!), and are defined in Python expression
		  syntax, which is very close to most other
		  languages. For example "3*x**2 + 2*x - 4". A number
		  of functions are available (e.g. sin, cos, tan, exp,
		  log...). Technically, Veusz imports the numpy
		  package when evaluating, so numpy functions are
		  available.</para>

		<para>As well as the function setting, also settable
		  is the line type to plot the function, and the
		  number of steps to evaluate the function when
		  plotting. Filling is supported
		  above/below/left/right of the function.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>xy</command> - a plotter which plots
		  scatter, line, or stepped plots. This versatile
		  plotter takes an x and y dataset, and plots
		  (optional) points, in a chosen marker and colour,
		  connecting them with (optional) lines, and plotting
		  (optional) error bars. An xy plotter can also plot a
		  stepped line, allowing histograms to be plotted
		  (note that it doesn't yet do the binning of the
		  data).</para>

		<para>The settings for the xy widget are the various
		  attibutes for the points, line and error bars, the
		  datasets to plot, and the axes to plot on.</para>

		<para>The xy plotter can plot a label next to each
		dataset, which is either the same for each point or
		taken from a text dataset.</para>

		<para>If you wish to leave gaps in a plot, the input
		value "nan" can be specified in the numeric
		dataset.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>fit</command> - fit a function to
		  data. This plotter is a like the function plotter,
		  but allows fitting of the function to data. This is
		  achived by clicking on a "fit" button, or using the
		  "fit" action of the widget. The fitter takes a
		  function to fit containing the unknowns,
		  e.g. "a*x**2 + b*x + c", and initial values for the
		  variables (here a, b and c). It then fits the data
		  (note that at the moment, the fit plotter fits all
		  the data, not just the data that can be seen on the
		  graph) by minimising the chi-squared.</para>

		<para>In order to fit properly, the y data (or x, if
		  fitting as a function of x) must have a properly
		  defined, preferably symmetric error. If there is
		  none, Veusz assumes the same fractional error
		  everywhere, or symmetrises asymmetric errors.</para>

		<para>Note that more work is required in this
		  widget, as if a parameter is not well defined by the
		  data, the matrix inversion in the fit will fail. In
		  addition Veusz does not supply estimates for the
		  errors or the final chi-squared in a machine
		  readable way.</para>

		<para>If the fitting parameters vary significantly
		from 1, then it is worth "normalizing" them by adding
		in a factor in the fit equation to bring them to of
		the order of 1.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>bar</command> - a bar chart which plots
		sets of data as horizontal or vertical bars. Multiple
		datasets are supported. In "grouped" mode the bars are
		placed side-by-side for each dataset. In "stacked"
		mode the bars are placed on top of each other (in the
		appropriate direction according to the sign of the
		dataset). Bars are placed on coordinates given, or in
		integer values from 1 upward if none are given. Error
		bars are plotted for each of the datasets.</para>

		<para>Different fill styles can be given for each
		dataset given. A separate key value can be given for
		each dataset.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>key</command> - a box which describes
		  the data plotted. If a key is added to a plot, the
		  key looks for "key" settings of the other data
		  plotted within a graph. If there any it builds up a
		  box containing the symbol and line for the plotter,
		  and the text in the "key" setting of the widget. This
		  allows a key to be very easily added to a
		  plot.</para>

		<para>The key may be placed in any of the corners of
		  the plot, in the centre, or manually
		  placed. Depending on the ordering of the widgets,
		  the key will be placed behind or on top of the
		  widget. The key can be filled and surrounded by a
		  box, or not filled or surrounded.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>label</command> - a text label places
		on a graph. The alignment can be adjusted and the font
		changed. The position of the label can be specified in
		fractional terms of the current graph, or using axis
		coordinates.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>rect, ellipse</command> - these draw a
		rectangle or ellipse, respectively, of size and
		rotation given. These widgets can be placed directly
		on the page or on a graph. The centre can be given in
		axis coordinates or fractional coordinates. </para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>imagefile</command> - draw an external
		graphs file on the graph or page, with size and
		rotation given. The centre can be given in axis
		coordinates or fractional coordinates.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>line</command> - draw a line with
		optional arrowheads on the graph or page. One end can
		be given in axis coordinates or fractional
		coordinates.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>contour</command> - plot contours of a
		2D dataset on the graph. Contours are automatically
		calculated between the minimum and maximum values of
		the graph or chosen manually. The line style of the
		contours can be chosen individually and the region
		between contours can be filled with shading or
		color.</para>

		<para>2D datasets currently consist of a regular grid
		of values between minimum and maximum positions in x
		and y. They can be constructed from three 1D datasets
		of x, y and z if they form a regular x, y grid.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>image</command> - plot a 2D dataset as
		a colored image. Different color schemes can be
		chosen. The scaling between the values and the image
		can be specified as linear, logarithmic, square-root
		or square.
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>polygon</command> - plot x and y points
		from datasets as a polygon. The polygon can be placed
		directly on the page or within a graph. Coordinates
		are either plotted using the axis or as fractions of
		the width and height of the containing widget.
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>boxplot</command> - plot distribution
		of points in a dataset.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>polar</command> - plot polar data or
		functions. This is a non-orthogonal plot and is placed
		directly on the page rather than in a graph.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><command>ternary</command> - plot data of three
		variables which add up to 100 per cent.This is a
		non-orthogonal plot and is placed directly on the page
		rather than in a graph.</para>
	      </listitem>

	    </orderedlist>

	  </listitem>

	</orderedlist>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Settings: properties and formatting</title>

	<para>The various settings of the widgets come in a number of
	types, including integers (e.g. 10), floats (e.g. 3.14),
	dataset names ("mydata"), expressions ("x+y"), text ("hi
	there!"), distances (see above), options ("horizontal" or
	"vertical" for axes).</para>

	<para>Veusz performs type checks on these parameters. If they
	are in the wrong format the control to edit the setting will
	turn red. In the command line, a TypeError exception is
	thrown.</para>

	<para>In the GUI, the current page is replotted if a setting
	is changed when enter is pressed or the user moves to another
	setting.</para>

	<para>The settings are split up into formatting settings,
	controlling the appearance of the plot, or properties,
	controlling what is plotted and how it is plotted.</para>

	<para>Default settings, including the default font and line
	style, and the default settings for any graph widget, can be
	modified in the "Default styles" dialog box under the "Edit"
	menu. Default settings are set on a per-document basis, but
	can be saved into a separate file and loaded. A default
	default settings file can be given to use for new documents
	(set in the preferences dialog).</para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="TextFonts" />Text</title>

	<para>Veusz understands a limited set of LaTeX-like formatting
	for text. There are some differences (for example, "10^23"
	puts the 2 and 3 into superscript), but it is fairly
	similar. You should also leave out the dollar signs. Veusz
	supports superscripts ("^"), subscripts ("_"), brackets for
	grouping attributes are "{" and "}".</para>

	<para>Supported LaTeX symbols include: \AA, \Alpha, \Beta,
 \Chi, \Delta, \Epsilon, \Eta, \Gamma, \Iota, \Kappa, \Lambda, \Mu,
 \Nu, \Omega, \Omicron, \Phi, \Pi, \Psi, \Rho, \Sigma, \Tau, \Theta,
 \Upsilon, \Xi, \Zeta, \alpha, \approx, \ast, \asymp, \beta, \bowtie,
 \bullet, \cap, \chi, \circ, \cup, \dagger, \dashv, \ddagger, \deg,
 \delta, \diamond, \divide, \doteq, \downarrow, \epsilon, \equiv,
 \eta, \gamma, \ge, \gg, \in, \infty, \int, \iota, \kappa, \lambda,
 \le, \leftarrow, \lhd, \ll, \models, \mp, \mu, \neq, \ni, \nu, \odot,
 \omega, \omicron, \ominus, \oplus, \oslash, \otimes, \parallel,
 \perp, \phi, \pi, \pm, \prec, \preceq, \propto, \psi, \rhd, \rho,
 \rightarrow, \sigma, \sim, \simeq, \sqrt, \sqsubset, \sqsubseteq,
 \sqsupset, \sqsupseteq, \star, \stigma, \subset, \subseteq, \succ,
 \succeq, \supset, \supseteq, \tau, \theta, \times, \umid, \unlhd,
 \unrhd, \uparrow, \uplus, \upsilon, \vdash, \vee, \wedge, \xi, \zeta.
 Please request additional characters if they are required (and exist
 in the unicode character set). Special symbols can be included
 directly from a character map.</para>

	 <para>Other LaTeX commands are supported. "\\" breaks a
	 line. This can be used for simple tables. For example "{a\\b}
	 {c\\d}" shows "a c" over "b d". The command "\frac{a}{b}"
	 shows a vertical fraction a/b.</para>

	<para>Also supported are commands to change font. The command
	"\font{name}{text}" changes the font text is written in to
	name. This may be useful if a symbol is missing from the
	current font, e.g. "\font{symbol}{g}" should produce a
	gamma. You can increase, decrease, or set the size of the font
	with "\size{+2}{text}", "\size{-2}{text}", or
	"\size{20}{text}". Numbers are in points.</para>

	<para>Various font attributes can be changed: for example,
	"\italic{some italic text}" (or use "\textit" or "\emph"),
	"\bold{some bold text}" (or use "\textbf") and "\underline{some
	underlined text}".</para>

	<para>Example text could include "Area / \pi (10^{-23}
	cm^{-2})", or "\pi\bold{g}".</para>

	<para>Veusz plots these symbols with Qt's unicode support. You
	can also include special characters directly, by copying and
	pasting from a character map application. If your current font
	does not contain these symbols then you may get a box
	character.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Measurements</title>

	<para>Distances, widths and lengths in Veusz can be specified
	in a number of different ways. These include absolute
	distances specified in physical units, e.g. 1cm, 0.05m, 10mm,
	5in and 10pt, and relative units, which are relative to
	the largest dimension of the page, including 5%, 1/20,
	0.05.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Axis numeric scales</title>

	<para>The way in which numbers are formatted in axis scales is
	chosen automatically. For standard numerical axes, values are
	shown with the "%Vg" formatting (see below). For date axes, an
	appropriate date formatting is used so that the interval shown
	is correct. A format can be given for an axis in the axis
	number formatting panel can be given to explicitly choose a
	format. Some examples are given in the drop down axis
	menu. Hold the mouse over the example for detail.</para>

	<para>C-style number formatting is used with a few Veusz
	specific extensions. Text can be mixed with format specifiers,
	which start with a "%" sign. Examples of C-style formatting
	include: "%.2f" (decimal number with two decimal places,
	e.g. 2.01), "%.3e" (scientific formatting with three decimal
	places, e.g. 2.123e-02), "%g" (general formatting, switching
	between "%f" and "%e" as appropriate). See <ulink
	url="http://opengroup.org/onlinepubs/007908799/xsh/fprintf.html"
	/> for details.</para>

	<para>Veusz extensions include "%Ve", which is like "%e"
	except it displays scientific notation as written,
	e.g. 1.2x10^23, rather than 1.2e+23. "%Vg" switches between
	standard numbers and Veusz scientific notation for large and
	small numbers. "%VE" using engineering SI suffixes to
	represent large or small numbers (e.g. 1000 is 1k).</para>

	<para>Veusz allows dates and times to be formatted using
	"%VDX" where "X" is one of the formatting characters for
	strftime (see
	<ulink url="http://opengroup.org/onlinepubs/007908799/xsh/strftime.html"
	/> for details). These include "a" for an abbreviated weekday
	name, "A" for full weekday name, "b" for abbreviated month
	name, "B" for full month name, "c" date and time
	representaiton, "d" day of month 01..31, "H" hour as 00..23,
	"I" hour as 01..12, "j" as day of year 001..366, "m" as month
	01..12, "M" minute as 00..59, "p" AM/PM, "S" second 00..61,
	"U" week number of year 00..53 (Sunday as first day of week),
	"w" weekday as decimal number 0..6, "W" week number of year
	(Monday as first day of week), "x" date representation, "X"
	time representation, "y" year without century 00..99 and "Y"
	year. "%VDVS" is a special Veusz addon format which shows
	seconds and fractions of seconds (e.g. 12.2).</para>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installation</title>

      <para>Please look at the Installation notes (INSTALL) for
      details on installing Veusz.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The main window</title>

      <para>You should see the main window when you run Veusz (you can
      just type the veusz command in Unix).</para>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="manimages/mainwindow.png" format="PNG" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The Veusz window is split into several sections. At the
      top is the menu bar and tool bar. These work in the usual way to
      other applications. Sometimes options are disabled (greyed out)
      if they do not make sense to be used. If you hold your mouse
      over a button for a few seconds, you will usually get an
      explanation for what it does called a "tool tip".</para>

      <para>Below the main toolbar is a second toolbar for
      constructing the graph by adding widgets (on the left), and some
      editing buttons. The add widget buttons add the request widget to
      the currently selected widget in the selection window. The widgets
      are arranged in a tree-like structure.</para>

      <para>Below these toolbars and to the right is the plot
      window. This is where the current page of the current document
      is shown. You can adjust the size of the plot on the screen (the
      zoom factor) using the "View" menu or the zoom tool bar button
      (the magnifying glass). Initially you will not see a plot in the
      plot window, but you will see the Veusz logo. At the moment you
      cannot do much else with the window. In the future you will be
      able to click on items in the plot to modify them.</para>

      <para>To the left of the plot window is the selection window,
      and the properties and formatting windows. The properties window
      lets you edit various aspects of the selected widget (such as the
      minimum and maximum values on an axis). Changing these values
      should update the plot. The formatting lets you modify the
      appearance of the selected widget. There are a series of tabs for
      choosing what aspect to modify.</para>

      <para>The various windows can be "dragged" from the main window
      to "float" by themselves on the screen.</para>

      <para>To the bottom of the window is the console. This window is
      not shown by default, but can be enabled in the View menu. The
      console is a Veusz and Python command line console. To read
      about the commands available
      see <link linkend="Commands">Commands</link>. As this is a
      Python console, you can enter mathematical expressions
      (e.g. "1+2.0*cos(pi/4)") here and they will be evaluated when
      you press Enter. The usual special functions and the operators
      are supported. You can also assign results to variables
      (e.g. "a=1+2") for use later. The console also supports command
      history like many Unix shells. Press the up and down cursor keys
      to browse through the history. Command line completion is not
      available yet!</para>

      <para>There also exists a dataset browsing window, by default to
      the right of the screen. This window allows you to view the
      datasets currently loaded, their dimensions and type. Hovering a
      mouse over the size of the dataset will give you a preview of
      the data.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>My first plot</title>

      <para>After opening Veusz, on the left of the main window, you
      will see a Document, containing a Page, which contains a Graph
      with its axes. The Graph is selected in the selection
      window. The toolbar above adds a new widget to the selected
      widget. If a widget cannot be added to a selected widget it is
      disabled. On opening a new document Veusz automatically adds a
      new Page and Graph (with axes) to the document.
</para>

      <para>You will see something like this:</para>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="manimages/winwithgraph.png" format="PNG" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Select the x axis which has been added to the document
      (click on "x" in the selection window). In the properties window
      you will see a variety of different properties you can
      modify. For instance you can enter a label for the axis by
      writing "Area (cm^{2})" in the box next to label and pressing
      enter. Veusz supports text in LaTeX-like form (without the
      dollar signs). Other important parameters is the "log" switch
      which switches between linear and logarithmic axes, and "min"
      and "max" which allow the user to specify the minimum and
      maximum values on the axes.</para>

      <para>The formatting dialog lets you edit various aspects of the
      graph appearance. For instance the "Line" tab allows you to edit
      the line of the axis. Click on "Line", then you can then modify
      its colour. Enter "green" instead of "black" and press
      enter. Try making the axis label bold.</para>

      <para>Now you can try plotting a function on the graph. If the
      graph, or its children are selected, you will then be able to
      click the "function" button at the top (a red curve on a
      graph). You will see a straight line (y=x) added to the plot. If
      you select "function1", you will be able to edit the functional
      form plotted and the style of its line. Change the function to
      "x**2" (x-squared).</para>

      <para>We will now try plotting data on the graph. Go to your
      favourite text editor and save the following data as
      test.dat:</para>

      <informalexample>
	<programlisting>
1     0.1   -0.12   1.1    0.1
2.05  0.12  -0.14   4.08   0.12
2.98  0.08  -0.1    2.9    0.11
4.02  0.04  -0.1    15.3   1.0
</programlisting>
	  </informalexample>

      <para>The first three columns are the x data to plot plus its
      asymmetric errors. The final two columns are the y data plus its
      symmetric errors. In Veusz, go to the "Data" menu and select
      "Import". Type the filename into the filename box, or use the
      "Browse..." button to search for the file. You will see a
      preview of the data pop up in the box below. Enter "x,+,- y,+-"
      into the descriptors edit box (note that commas and spaces in
      the descriptor are almost interchangeable in Veusz 1.6 or
      newer). This describes the format of the data which describes
      dataset "x" plus its asymmetric errors, and "y" with its
      symmetric errors. If you now click "Import", you will see it has
      imported datasets "x" and "y".</para>

      <para>To plot the data you should now click on "graph1" in the
      tree window. You are now able to click on the "xy" button (which
      looks like points plotted on a graph). You will see your data
      plotted on the graph. Veusz plots datasets "x" and "y" by
      default, but you can change these in the properties of the "xy"
      plotter.</para>

      <para>You are able to choose from a variety of markers to
      plot. You can remove the plot line by choosing the "Plot Line"
      subsetting, and clicking on the "hide" option. You can change
      the colour of the marker by going to the "Marker Fill"
      subsetting, and entering a new colour (e.g. red), into the
      colour property.</para>
    </section>

  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Reading data</title>

    <para>
      Currently Veusz supports reading data from files with text, CSV,
      HDF5, FITS, 2D text, QDP, binary and NPY/NPZ formats. Use the
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Data</guimenu><guimenuitem>Import</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
      dialog to read data, or the importing commands in the API can be
      used.  In addition, the user can load or write import plugins in
      Python which load data into Veusz in an arbitrary format. At the
      moment QDP, binary and NPY/NPZ files are supported with this
      method. The HDF5 file format is the most sophisticated, and is
      recommended for complex datasets.
    </para>

    <para>
      By default, data are "linked" to the file imported from. This
      means that the data are not stored in the Veusz saved file and
      are reloaded from the original data file when opening. In
      addition, the user can use the
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Data</guimenu><guimenuitem>Reload</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
      menu option to reload data from linked files. Unselect the
      linked option when importing to remove the association with the
      data file and to store the data in the Veusz saved document.
    </para>

    <para>
      Note that a <symbol>prefix</symbol> and
      <symbol>suffix</symbol> can be given when importing. These are
      added to the front or back of each dataset name imported. They
      are convenient for grouping data together.
    </para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="manimages/importdialog.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>We list the various types of import below.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Standard text import</title>

      <para>
	The default text import operates on simple text files. The
	data are assumed to be in columns separated by
	whitespace. Each column corresponds to dataset (or its error
	bars). Each row is an entry in the dataset.
      </para>

      <para>
	The way the data are read is goverened by a simple
	"descriptor". This can simply be a list of dataset names
	separated by spaces. If no descriptor is given, the columns
	are treated as separate datasets and are given names
	<symbol>col1</symbol>, <symbol>col2</symbol>, etc. Veusz
	attempts to automatically determine the type of the data.
      </para>

      <para>
	When reading in data, Veusz treats any whitespace as
	separating columns. The columns do not actually need to be
	aligned. Furthermore a "\" symbol can be placed at the end of
	a line to mark a continuation. Veusz will read the next line
	as if it were placed at the end of the current line. In
	addition comments and blank lines are ignored (unless in block
	mode). Comments start with a "#", ";", "!" or "%", and
	continue until the end of the line. The special value "nan"
	can be used to specify a break in a dataset.
      </para>

      <para>
	If the option to read data in blocks is enabled, Veusz treats
	blank lines (or lines starting with the word "no") as block
	separators. For each dataset in the descriptor, separate
	datasets are created for each block, using a numeric suffix
	giving the block number, e.g. <symbol>_1</symbol>,
	<symbol>_2</symbol>.
      </para>

      <section>
	<title>Data types in text import</title>

	<para>
	  Veusz supports reading in several types of data. The type of
	  data can be added in round brackets after the name in the
	  descriptor. Veusz will try to guess the type of data based
	  on the first value, so you should specify it if there is any
	  form of ambiguity (e.g. is 3 text or a number). Supported
	  types are numbers (use numeric in brackets) and text (use
	  text in brackets). An example descriptor would be
	  "x(numeric) +- y(numeric) + - label(text)" for an x dataset
	  followed by its symmetric errors, a y dataset followed by
	  two columns of asymmetric errors, and a final column of text
	  for the label dataset.
	</para>

	<para>
	  A text column does not need quotation unless it contains
	  space characters or escape characters. However make sure you
	  deselect the "ignore text" option in the import dialog. This
	  ignores lines of text to ease the import of data from other
	  applications.  Quotation marks are recommended around text
	  if you wish to avoid ambiguity. Text is quoted according to
	  the Python rules for text. Double or single quotation marks
	  can be used, e.g. "A 'test'", 'A second "test"'. Quotes can
	  be escaped by prefixing them with a backslash, e.g. "A new
	  \"test\"". If the data are generated from a Python script,
	  the repr function provides the text in a suitable form.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Dates and times are also supported with the syntax
	  "dataset(date)". Dates must be in ISO format
	  YYYY-MM-DD. Times are in 24 hour format hh:mm:ss.ss. Dates
	  with times are written YYYY-MM-DDThh:mm:ss.ss (this is a
	  standard ISO format, see <ulink
	  url="http://www.w3.org/TR/NOTE-datetime" />). Dates are
	  stored within Veusz as a number which is the number of
	  seconds since the start of January 1st 2009. Veusz also
	  supports dates and times in the local format, though take
	  note that the same file and data may not work on a system in
	  a different location.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Descriptors" />Descriptors</title>

	<para>
	  A list of datasets, or a "Descriptor", is given in the
	  Import dialog to describe how the data are formatted in the
	  import file. The descriptor at its simplest is a space or
	  comma-separated list of the names of the datasets to import.
	  These are columns in the file.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Following a dataset name the text "+", "-", or "+-" can be
	  given to say that the following column is a positive error
	  bar, negative error bar or symmetric error bar for the
	  previous (non error bar) dataset. These symbols should be
	  separated from the dataset name or previous symbol with a
	  space or a comma symbol.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In addition, if multiple numbered columns should be
	  imported, the dataset name can be followed by square
	  brackets containing a range in the form "[a:b]" to number
	  columns a to b, or [:] to number remaining columns. See
	  below for examples of this use.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Dataset names can contain virtually any character, even
	  unicode characters. If the name contains non alpha-numeric
	  characters (characters outside of A-Z, a-z and 0-9), then
	  the dataset name should be contained within back-tick
	  characters. An example descriptor is <command>`length data
	  (m)`,+- `speed (mps)`,+,-</command>, for two datasets with
	  spaces and brackets in their names.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Instead of specifying the descriptor in the Import dialog,
	  the descriptor can be placed in the data file using a
	  descriptor statement on a separate line, consisting of
	  "descriptor" followed by the descriptor. Multiple
	  descriptors can be placed in a single file, for example:
	</para>
	<informalexample>
	  <programlisting>
# here is one section
descriptor x,+- y,+,-
1 0.5  2 0.1 -0.1
2 0.3  4 0.2 -0.1

# my next block
descriptor alpha beta gamma
1 2 3
4 5 6
7 8 9

# etc...
</programlisting>
	</informalexample>

	<section>
	 <title>Descriptor examples</title>
	 <orderedlist>
	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <command>x y</command> two columns are present in the
	       file, they will be read in as datasets "x" and "y".
	     </para>
	   </listitem>

	   <listitem>
	     <para>
	       <command>x,+- y,+,-</command> or <command>x +- y +
	       -</command> two datasets are in the file. Dataset "x"
	       consists of the first two columns. The first column are
	       the values and the second are the symmetric errors. "y"
	       consists of three columns (note the comma between + and
	       -). The first column are the values, the second
	       positive asymmetric errors, and the third negative
	       asymmetric errors.
	     </para>

	  <para>
	    Suppose the input file contains:
	  </para>
	  <informalexample>
	    <programlisting>
1.0  0.3  2   0.1  -0.2
1.5  0.2  2.3 2e-2 -0.3E0
2.19 0.02 5    0.1 -0.1
</programlisting>
	  </informalexample>

	  <para>
	    Then x will contain "1+-0.3", "1.5+-0.2",
	    "2.19+-0.02". y will contain "2 +0.1 -0.2", "2.3 +0.02
	    -0.3", "5 +0.1 -0.1".
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <command>x[1:2] y[:]</command> the first column is the
	    data "x_1", the second "x_2". Subsequent columns are read
	    as "y[1]" to "y[n]".
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <command>y[:]+-</command> read each pair of columns as
	    a dataset and its symmetric error, calling them "y[1]" to
	    "y[n]".
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <command>foo,,+-</command>  read the first column as
	    the foo dataset, skip a column, and read the third column as
	    its symmetric error.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	 </orderedlist>
	</section>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>CSV files</title>

      <para>
	CVS (comma separated variable) files are often written from
	other programs, such as spreadsheets, including Excel and
	Gnumeric. Veusz supports reading from these files.
      </para>

      <para>
	In the import dialog choose "CSV", then choose a filename to
	import from. In the CSV file the user should place the data in
	either rows or columns. Veusz will use a name above a column
	or to the left of a row to specify what the dataset name
	should be. The user can use new names further down in columns
	or right in rows to specify a different dataset name. Names do
	not have to be used, and Veusz will assign default "col" and
	"row" names if not given. You can also specify a prefix which
	is prepended to each dataset name read from the file.
      </para>

      <para>
	To specify symmetric errors for a column, put "+-" as the
	dataset name in the next column or row. Asymmetric errors can
	be stated with "+" and "-" in the columns.
      </para>

      <para>
	The data type in CSV files are automatically detected unless
	specified. The data type can be given in brackets after the
	column name, e.g. "name (text)", where the data type is
	"date", "numeric" or "text". Explicit data types are needed if
	the data look like a different data type (e.g. a text item of
	"1.23"). The date format in CSV files can be specified in the
	import dialog box - see the examples given. In addition CSV
	files support numbers in European format (e.g. 2,34 rather
	than 2.34), depending on the setting in the dialog box.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>HDF5 files</title>

      <para>
	HDF5 is a flexible data format. Datasets and tables can be
	stored in a hierarchical arrangements of groups within a
	file. Veusz supports reading 1D numeric, text, date-time or 2D
	numeric data from HDF files. The <command>h5py</command>
	Python module must be installed to use HDF5 files (included in
	binary releases).
      </para>

      <para>
	In the import dialog box, choose which individual datasets to
	import, or selecting a group to import all the datasets within
	the group. If selecting a group, datasets in the group
	incompatible with Veusz are ignored.
      </para>

      <para>
	A name can be provided for each dataset imported by entering
	one under "Import as". If one is not given, the dataset or
	column name is used. The name can also be specified by setting
	the HDF5 dataset attribute <varname>vsz_name</varname> to the
	name. Note that for compound datasets (tables),
	<varname>vsz_</varname> attributes for columns are given by
	appending the suffix <varname>_columnname</varname> to the
	attribute.
      </para>

      <section>
	<title>Error bars</title>
	<para>
	  Error bars are supported in two ways. The first way is to
	  combine 1D datasets. For the datasets which are error bars,
	  use a name which is the same as the main dataset but with
	  the suffix "(+-)", "(+)" or "(-)", for symmetric, postive or
	  negative error bars, respectively. The second method is to
	  use a 2D dataset with two or three columns, for symmetric or
	  asymmetric error bars, respectively. Click on the dataset in
	  the dialog and choose the option to import as a 1D
	  dataset. This second method can also be enabled by adding an
	  HDF5 attribute <varname>vsz_twod_as_oned</varname> set to a
	  non-zero value for the dataset.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Slices</title>
	<para>
	  As Veusz only supports 1D and 2D datasets, you may wish to
	  reduce the dimensions of a dataset before importing by
	  slicing. You can also give a slice to import a subset of a
	  dataset. When importing, in the slice column you can give a
	  slice expression. This should have the same number of
	  entries as the dataset has dimensions, separated by
	  commas. An entry can be a single number, to select a
	  particular row or column. Alternatively it could be an
	  expression like <literal>a:b:c</literal> or
	  <literal>a:b</literal>, where <literal>a</literal> is the
	  starting index, <literal>b</literal> is one beyond the
	  stopping index and optionally <literal>c</literal> is the
	  step size. A slice can also be specified by providing an
	  HDF5 attribute <varname>vsz_slice</varname> for the dataset.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>2D data ranges</title>
	<para>
	  2D data have an associated X and Y range. By default the
	  number of pixels of the image are used to give this range.
	  A range can be specified by clicking on the dataset and
	  entering a minimum and maximum X and Y
	  coordinates. Alternatively, provide the HDF5 attribute for
	  the dataset <varname>vsz_range</varname>, which should be set
	  to an array of four values (minimum x, minimum y, maximum x,
	  maximum y).
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Dates</title>
	<para>
	  Date/time datasets can be made from a 1D numeric dataset or
	  from a text dataset. For the 1D dataset, use the number of
	  seconds relative to the start of the year 2009 (this is
	  Veusz format) or the year 1970 (this is Unix format). In the
	  import dialog, click on the name of the dataset and choose
	  the date option. To specify a date format in the HDF5 file,
	  set the attribute <varname>vsz_convert_datetime</varname> to
	  either <literal>veusz</literal> or <literal>unix</literal>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  For text datasets, dates must be given in the right format,
	  selected in the import dialog after clicking on the dataset
	  name. As in other file formats, by default Veusz uses ISO
	  8601 format, which looks like "2013-12-22T21:08:07", where
	  the date and time parts are optional. The T is also
	  optional. You can also provide your own format when
	  importing by giving a date expression using YYYY, MM, DD,
	  hh, mm and ss (e.g. "YYYY-MM-DD|T|hh:mm:ss"), where vertical
	  bars mark optional parts of the expression. To automate
	  this, set the attribute
	  <varname>vsz_convert_datetime</varname> to the format
	  expression or <literal>iso</literal> to specify ISO format.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>2D text</title>
      <para>
	Veusz can import 2D data from standard text files. In this
	case the data should consist of a matrix of data values, with
	the columns separated by one or more spaces or tabs and the
	rows on different lines.
      </para>

    <para>
      In addition to the data the file can contain lines at the top
      which affect the import. Such specifiers are used, for example,
      to change the coordinates of the pixels in the file. By default
      the first pixels coordinates is between 0 and 1, with the centre
      at 0.5. Subsequent pixels are 1 greater. Below are listed the
      specifiers:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para><command>xrange A B</command> - make the 2D dataset span
	the coordinate range A to B in the x-axis (where A and B are
	numbers). Note that the range is inclusive, so a 1 pixel wide
	image with A=0 and B=1 would have the pixel centre at
	0.5. The pixels are assumed to have the same spacing. Do not
	use this as the same time as <command>xgrid</command>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><command>yrange A B</command> - make the 2D dataset span
	the coordinate range A to B in the y-axis (where A and B are
	numbers).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><command>xgrid [cen|cen_log] A B C...</command> - rather
	than assume the pixels have the same spacing, give the
	coordinates of the edges of the pixels in the x-axis. The
	numbers should be space-separated and there should be one more
	number than pixels. Do not give <command>xrange</command> if
	this is given.</para>

	<para>
	  If the optional argument <literal>cen</literal> or
	  <literal>cen_log</literal> is given, then give the centres
	  of the pixels. In this case the edges are assumed to lie to
	  half way between the centres (in log space for
	  <literal>cen_log</literal>). The edges of the outer pixels
	  are calculated by assuming that they have the same width
	  from their centres to either edge. Note that the calculated
	  edges will not necessarily give the correct centres when
	  plotting.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><command>ygrid [cen|cen_log] A B C...</command> - rather than assume
	the pixels have the same spacing, give the coordinates of the
	edges of the pixels in the y-axis.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><command>invertrows</command> - invert the rows after
	reading the data.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><command>invertcols</command> - invert the columns after
	reading the data.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><command>transpose</command> - swap rows and columns
	after importing data.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>FITS files</title>
      <para>
	1D or 2D data can be read from FITS files. 1D data, with
	optional errors bars, can be read from table extensions, and
	2D data from image or primary extensions.  Note that pyfits or
	astropy must be installed to get FITS support.
      </para>

      <para>
	To read 1D data, choose a tabular HDU for to import from,
	enter the name to give the imported data, and choose the
	columns to assign to the data. Multiple sets of data can be
	read by repeatedly importing.
      </para>

      <para>
	For 2D data, choose an image HDU. Enter the name of the
	dataset. The data are imported with pixel coordinates by
	default (i.e. the pixels are numbered with integers). Other
	modes can be selected under <guilabel>Image WCS
	mode</guilabel>. These include fractional, where the pixels
	are numbered between 0 and 1. <guilabel>Pixel (WCS)</guilabel>
	assigns the pixel coordinate calculated relative to the
	<varname>CRPIX1/2</varname> header keywords. <guilabel>Linear
	(WCS)</guilabel> uses linear coordinates where the Pixel (WCS)
	coordinates are multiplied by the respective
	<varname>CDELT1/2</varname> values and added to the
	<varname>CRVAL1/2</varname> values.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Reading other data formats</title>

      <para>As mentioned above, a user may write some Python code to
      read a data file or set of data files. To write a plugin which
      is incorportated into Veusz, see
      <ulink url="http://barmag.net/veusz-wiki/ImportPlugins"
      /></para>

      <para>You can also include Python code in an input file to read
      data, which we describe here. Suppose an input file "in.dat"
      contains the following data:</para>
      <informalexample>
	<programlisting>
1   2
2   4
3   9
4   16
</programlisting>
	  </informalexample>

      <para>Of course this data could be read using the <link
	linkend="Command.ImportFile">ImportFile</link>
	command. However, you could also read it with the following
	Veusz script (which could be saved to a file and loaded with
	<command>execfile</command> or <link
	linkend="Command.Load">Load</link>. The script also places
	symmetric errors of 0.1 on the x dataset.</para>

      <informalexample>
	<programlisting>
x = []
y = []
for line in open("in.dat"):
    parts = [float(i) for i in line.split()]
    x.append(parts[0])
    y.append(parts[1])

SetData('x', x, symerr=0.1)
SetData('y', y)
</programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Manipulating datasets</title>

      <para>Imported datasets can easily be modified in the Data
      Editor dialog box. This dialog box can also be used to create
      new datasets from scratch by typing them in. The Data Create
      dialog box is used to new datasets as a numerical sequence,
      parametrically or based on other datasets given expressions. If
      you want to plot a function of a dataset, you often do not have
      to create a new dataset. Veusz allows to enter expressions
      directly in many places.</para>

      <section>
	<title>Using dataset plugins</title>
	<para>Dataset plugins can be used to perform arbitrary
	manipulation of datasets. Veusz includes several plugins for
	mathematical operation of data and other dataset
	manipulations, such as concatenation or splitting. If you wish
	to write your own plugins look at
	<ulink url="http://barmag.net/veusz-wiki/DatasetPlugins"
	/>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Using expressions to create new datasets</title>
      <para>For instance, if the user has already imported dataset d,
      then they can create d2 which consists of d**2. Expressions are
      in Python numpy syntax and can include the usual mathematical
      functions.</para>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="manimages/createdataset.png" format="PNG" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Expressions for error bars can also be given. By appending
      <command>_data</command>, <command>_serr</command>,
      <command>_perr</command> or <command>_nerr</command> to the name
      of the dataset in the expression, the user can base their
      expression on particular parts of the given dataset (the main
      data, symmetric errors, positive errors or negative
      errors). Otherwise the program uses the same parts as is
      currently being specified.</para>

      <para>If a dataset name contains non alphanumeric characters,
      its name should be quoted in the expression in back-tick
      characters, e.g. <command>`length (cm)`*2</command>.</para>

      <para>The numpy functionality is particularly useful for doing
      more complicated expressions. For instance, a conditional
      expression can be written as
      <command>where(x&lt;y,x,y)</command> or
      <command>where(isfinite(x),a,b))</command>.</para>

      <para>You often do not need to create a new dataset when. For
      example, with the xy point plotter widget, you can directly
      enter an expression as the X and Y dataset settings. When you
      give a direct dataset expression, you can define error bar
      expressions by separating them by commas, and optionally
      surrounding them by brackets. For example
      <command>(a,0.1)</command> plots dataset a as the data, with
      symmetric errors bars of 0.1. Asymmetric bars are given as
      <command>(a,a*0.1,-a*0.1)</command>.</para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Linking datasets to expressions</title>
      <para>A particularly useful feature is to be able to link a
      dataset to an expression, so if the expression changes the
      dataset changes with it, like in a spreadsheet.</para>
      </section>


      <section>
	<title>Splitting data</title>
	<para>Data can also be chopped in this method, for example
      using the expression <command>x[10:20]</command>, which makes a
      dataset based on the 11th to 20th item in the x dataset (the
      ranges are Python syntax, and are zero-based). Negative indices
      count backwards from the end of the dataset. Data can be skipped
      using expressions such as
	  <command>data[::2]</command>, which skips every other element</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Defining new constants or functions</title>
	<para>User defined constants or functions can be defined in
	the "Custom definitions" dialog box under the edit
	menu. Functions can also be imported from external python
	modules.</para>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="manimages/customdefinition.png" format="PNG" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>

	<para>Custom definitions are defined on a per-document basis,
	but can be saved or loaded into a file. A default custom
	definitions file can be set in the preferences dialog
	box.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Dataset plugins</title>
	<para>In addition to creating datasets based on expressions, a
	variety of dataset plugins exist, which make certain
	operations on datasets much more convenient. See the Data,
	Operations menu for a list of the default plugins. The user
	can easily create new plugins. See
	<ulink
	url="http://barmag.net/veusz-wiki/DatasetPlugins" /> for details.
	</para>
      </section>

    </section>

  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><anchor id="Commands" />Command line interface</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>An alternative way to control Veusz is via its command
      line interface. As Veusz is a a Python application it uses
      Python as its scripting language. Therefore you can freely mix
      Veusz and Python commands on the command line. Veusz can also
      read in Python scripts from files (see the <link
      linkend="Command.Load">Load</link> command).</para>

      <para>When commands are entered in the command prompt in the
      Veusz window, Veusz supports a simplified command syntax, where
      brackets following commands names, and commas, can replaced by
      spaces in Veusz commands (not Python commands). For example,
      <command>Add('graph', name='foo')</command>, may be entered as
      <command>Add 'graph' name='foo'</command>.</para>

      <para>The <command>numpy</command> package is already
      imported into the command line interface (as "*"), so you do not
      need to import it first.</para>

      <para>The command prompt supports history (use the up and down cursor
      keys to recall previous commands). </para>

      <para>Most of the commands listed below can be used in the
      in-program command line interface, using the embedding interface
      or using veusz_listen. Commands specific to particular modes are
      documented as such.</para>

      <para>Veusz also includes a new object-oriented version of the
      interface, which is documented at
      <ulink url="http://barmag.net/veusz-wiki/EmbeddingPython"
      />.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Commands</title>

      <para>We list the allowed set of commands below</para>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Action" />Action</title>

	<para><command>Action('actionname',
	componentpath='.')</command></para>

	<para>Initiates the specified action on the widget (component)
	given the action name. Actions perform certain automated
	routines. These include "fit" on a fit widget, and
	"zeroMargins" on grids.</para> </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Add" />Add</title>

	<para><command>Add('widgettype', name='nameforwidget',
        autoadd=True, optionalargs)</command></para>

	<para>The Add command adds a graph into the current widget
        (See the <link linkend="Command.To">To</link> command to change
        the current position).</para>

	<para>The first argument is the type of widget to add. These
        include "graph", "page", "axis", "xy" and
        "grid". <command>name</command> is the name of the new widget
        (if not given, it will be generated from the type of the
        widget plus a number). The <command>autoadd</command>
        parameter if set, constructs the default sub-widgets this
        widget has (for example, axes in a graph).</para>

	<para>Optionally, default values for the graph settings may be
        given, for example <command>Add('axis', name='y',
        direction='vertical')</command>.</para>

	<para>Subsettings may be set by using double underscores, for
	example <command>Add('xy',
	MarkerFill__color='red', ErrorBarLine__hide=True)</command>.</para>

	<para>Returns: Name of widget added.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.AddCustom" />AddCustom</title>

	<para><command>AddCustom(type, name, value)</command></para>

	<para>Add a custom definition for evaluation of
	expressions. This can define a constant (can be in terms of
	other constants), a function of 1 or more variables, or a
	function imported from an external python module.</para>

        <para>ctype is "constant", "function" or "import".</para>

        <para>name is name of constant, or "function(x, y, ...)" or
        module name.</para>

        <para>val is definition for constant or function (both are
        _strings_), or is a list of symbols for a module (comma
        separated items in a string).</para>

        <para>If mode is 'appendalways', the custom value is appended
        to the end of the list even if there is one with the same
        name. If mode is 'replace', it replaces any existing
        definition in the same place in the list or is appended
        otherwise. If mode is 'append', then an existing definition is
        deleted, and the new one appended to the end.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.AddImportPath" />AddImportPath</title>

	<para><command>AddImportPath(directory)</command></para>

	<para>Add a directory to the list of directories to try to
	import data from.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.CloneWidget" />CloneWidget</title>

	<para><command>CloneWidget(widget, newparent,
	newname=None)</command></para>

	<para>Clone the widget given, placing the copy in newparent
        and the name given.  newname is an optional new name to give
        it Returns new widget path.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Close" />Close</title>

	<para><command>Close()</command></para>

	<para>Closes the plotwindow. This is only supported in
	embedded mode.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.CreateHistogram" />CreateHistogram</title>

	<para><command>CreateHistogram(inexpr, outbinsds,
                        outvalsds, binparams=None, binmanual=None,
                        method='counts', cumulative = 'none',
                        errors=False)</command></para>

	<para>
	  Histogram an input expression.  inexpr is input expression.
        outbinds is the name of the dataset to create giving bin
        positions.  outvalsds is name of dataset for bin values.
        binparams is None or (numbins, minval, maxval, islogbins).
        binmanual is None or a list of bin values.  method is
        'counts', 'density', or 'fractions'.  cumulative is to
        calculate cumulative distributions which is 'none',
        'smalltolarge' or 'largetosmall'.  errors is to calculate
        Poisson error bars.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.DatasetPlugin" />DatasetPlugin</title>

	<para><command>DatasetPlugin(pluginname, fields,
	datasetnames={})></command></para>

	<para>
	  Use a dataset plugin.  pluginname: name of plugin to use
        fields: dict of input values to plugin datasetnames: dict
        mapping old names to new names of datasets if they are
        renamed. The new name None means dataset is deleted
	  </para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.EnableToolbar"
	/>EnableToolbar</title>

	<para><command>EnableToolbar(enable=True)</command></para>

	<para>Enable/disable the zooming toolbar in the
	plotwindow. This command is only supported in embedded mode or
	from veusz_listen.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Export" />Export</title>

	<para><command>Export(filename, color=True,
      page=0 dpi=100,
      antialias=True, quality=85, backcolor='#ffffff00',
	pdfdpi=150, svgtextastext=False)</command></para>

	<para>Export the page given to the filename given. The
	<command>filename</command> must end with the correct
	extension to get the right sort of output file. Currrenly
	supported extensions are '.eps', '.pdf', '.svg', '.jpg',
	'.jpeg', '.bmp' and '.png'. If <command>color</command> is
	True, then the output is in colour, else
	greyscale. <command>page</command> is the page number of the
	document to export (starting from 0 for the first page!).
	<command>dpi</command> is the number of dots per inch for
	bitmap output files.  <command>antialias</command> -
	antialiases output if True. <command>quality</command> is a
	quality parameter for jpeg
	output. <command>backcolor</command> is the background color
	for bitmap files, which is a name or a #RRGGBBAA value (red,
	green, blue, alpha). <command>pdfdpi</command> is the dpi to
	use when exporting EPS or PDF
	files. <command>svgtextastext</command> says whether to export
	SVG text as text, rather than curves.
</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.ForceUpdate" />ForceUpdate</title>

	<para><command>ForceUpdate()</command></para>

	<para>Force the window to be updated to reflect the current
	state of the document. Often used when periodic updates have
	been disabled (see SetUpdateInterval). This command is only
	supported in embedded mode or from veusz_listen.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Get" />Get</title>

	<para><command>Get('settingpath')</command></para>

	<para>Returns: The value of the setting given by the path.</para>

	<informalexample>
	  <programlisting>
>>> Get('/page1/graph1/x/min')
'Auto'
</programlisting>
	</informalexample>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.GetChildren" />GetChildren</title>

	<para><command>GetChildren(where='.')</command></para>

	<para>Returns: The names of the widgets which are children of
      the path given</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.GetClick" />GetClick</title>

	<para><command>GetClick()</command></para>

	<para>Waits for the user to click on a graph and returns the
	position of the click on appropriate axes. Command only works
	in embedded mode.</para>

	<para>Returns: A list containing tuples of the form (axispath,
	val) for each axis for which the click was in range. The value
	is the value on the axis for the click.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.GetData" />GetData</title>
	<para><command>GetData(name)</command></para>

	<para>Returns: For a 1D dataset, a tuple containing the
	dataset with the name given. The value is (data, symerr,
	negerr, poserr), with each a numpy array of the same size or
	None. data are the values of the dataset, symerr are the
	symmetric errors (if set), negerr and poserr and negative and
	positive asymmetric errors (if set). If a text dataset, return
	a list of text elements. If the dataset is a date-time
	dataset, return a list of Python datetime objects. If the
	dataset is a 2D dataset return the tuple (data, rangex,
	rangey), where data is a 2D numpy array and rangex/y are
	tuples giving the range of the x and y coordinates of the
	data.</para>

	<informalexample>
	  <programlisting>
data = GetData('x')
SetData('x', data[0]*0.1, *data[1:])
</programlisting>
	</informalexample>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.GetDataType" />GetDataType</title>
	<para><command>GetDataType(name)</command></para>

	<para>Get type of dataset with name given. Returns '1d' for a
	1d dataset, '2d' for a 2d dataset, 'text' for a text dataset
	and 'datetime' for a datetime dataset.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.GetDatasets" />GetDatasets</title>

	<para><command>GetDatasets()</command></para>

	<para>Returns: The names of the datasets in the current
      document.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.GPL" />GPL</title>

	<para><command>GPL()</command></para>

	<para>Print out the GNU Public Licence, which Veusz is licenced
      under.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.ImportFile" />ImportFile</title>

	<para><command>ImportFile('filename', 'descriptor',
	    linked=False, prefix='', suffix='',
	    encoding='utf_8')</command></para>

	<para>Imports data from a file. The arguments are the filename
	to load data from and the descriptor.</para>

	<para>The format of the descriptor is a list of variable names
        representing the columns of the data. For more information see
        <link linkend="Descriptors">Descriptors</link>.</para>

	<para>If the linked parameter is set to True, if the document
	is saved, the data imported will not be saved with the
	document, but will be reread from the filename given the next
	time the document is opened. The linked parameter is
	optional.</para>

	<para>If prefix and/or suffix are set, then the prefix and
	suffix are added to each dataset name.</para>

	<para>Returns: A tuple containing a list of the imported
	datasets and the number of conversions which failed for a
	dataset.</para>

	<para>Changed in version 0.5: A tuple is returned rather than
	just the number of imported variables.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.ImportFile2D" />ImportFile2D</title>

	<para><command>ImportFile2D('filename', datasets,
xrange=(a,b), yrange=(c,d), invertrows=True/False,
invertcols=True/False, transpose=True/False,
prefix='', suffix='', linked=False,
encoding='utf8')</command></para>

	<para>Imports two-dimensional data from a file. The required
	arguments are the filename to load data from and the dataset
	name, or a list of names to use.</para>

	<para>filename is a string which contains the filename to
	use. datasets is either a string (for a single dataset), or a
	list of strings (for multiple datasets).</para>

	<para>The xrange parameter is a tuple which contains the range
	of the X-axis along the two-dimensional dataset, for example
	(-1., 1.) represents an inclusive range of -1 to 1. The yrange
	parameter specifies the range of the Y-axis similarly. If they
	are not specified, (0, N) is the default, where N is the
	number of datapoints along a particular axis.</para>

	<para>invertrows and invertcols if set to True, invert the
	rows and columns respectively after they are read by
	Veusz. transpose swaps the rows and columns.</para>

	<para>If prefix and/or suffix are set, they are prepended or
	appended to imported dataset names.</para>

	<para>If the linked parameter is True, then the datasets are
	linked to the imported file, and are not saved within a saved
	document.</para>

	<para>The file format this command accepts is a
	two-dimensional matrix of numbers, with the columns separated
	by spaces or tabs, and the rows separated by new
	lines. The X-coordinate is taken to be in the direction of the
	columns. Comments are supported (use "#", "!" or "%"), as are
	continuation characters ("\"). Separate datasets are
	deliminated by using blank lines.</para>

	<para>In addition to the matrix of numbers, the various
	optional parameters this command takes can also be specified
	in the data file. These commands should be given on separate
	lines before the matrix of numbers. They are:</para>
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem><para>xrange A B</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>yrange C D</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>invertrows</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>invertcols</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>transpose</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.ImportFileCSV" />ImportFileCSV</title>

	<para><command>ImportFileCSV('filename', readrows=False,
	    dsprefix='', dssuffix='', linked=False, encoding='utf_8')
	</command></para>

	<para>This command imports data from a CSV format file. Data
	  are read from the file using the dataset names given at the
	  top of the files in columns. Please see the reading data
	  section of this manual for more information. dsprefix is
	  prepended to each dataset name and dssuffix is added (the
	  prefix option is deprecated and also addeds an underscore to
	  the dataset name). linked specifies whether the data will be
	  linked to the file.
	</para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.ImportFilePlugin" />ImportFilePlugin</title>

	<para><command>ImportFilePlugin('pluginname', 'filename',
	    **pluginargs, linked=False, encoding='utf_8',
	    prefix='', suffix='')</command></para>

	<para>
	  Import data from file using import plugin 'pluginname'. The
	  arguments to the plugin are given, plus optionally a text
	  encoding, and prefix and suffix to prepend or append to
	  dataset names.
	</para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.ImportFITSFile" />
	    ImportFITSFile</title>

	<para><command>ImportFITSFile(datasetname, filename, hdu,
	    datacol='A', symerrcol='B', poserrcol='C', negerrcol='D',
	    linked=True/False)</command></para>

	<para>This command does a simple import from a FITS file. The
FITS format is used within the astronomical community to transport
binary data. For a more powerful FITS interface, you can use PyFITS
within your scripts.</para>

	<para>The datasetname is the name of the dataset to import,
the filename is the name of the FITS file to import from. The hdu
parameter specifies the HDU to import data from (numerical or a
name).</para>

	<para>If the HDU specified is a primary HDU or image
	extension, then a two-dimensional dataset is loaded from the
	file. The optional parameters (other than linked) are
	ignored. Any WCS information within the HDU are used to
	provide a suitable xrange and yrange.</para>

	<para>If the HDU is a table, then the datacol parameter must
	be specified (and optionally symerrcol, poserrcol and
	negerrcol). The dataset is read in from the named column in
	the table. Any errors are read in from the other specified
	columns.</para>

	<para>If linked is True, then the dataset is not saved with a
	saved document, but is reread from the data file each time the
	document is loaded.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.ImportString" />ImportString</title>

	<para><command>ImportString('descriptor',
	'data')</command></para>

	<para>Like, <link
	linkend="Command.ImportFile">ImportFile</link>, but loads the
	data from the specfied string rather than a file. This allows
	data to be easily embedded within a document. The data string is
	usually a multi-line Python string.</para>

	<para>Returns: A tuple containing a list of the imported
	datasets and the number of conversions which failed for a
	dataset.</para>

	<para>Changed in version 0.5: A tuple is returned rather than
	just the number of imported variables.</para>

	<informalexample>
	  <programlisting>
ImportString('x y', '''
1   2
2   5
3   10
''')
</programlisting>
	</informalexample>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor
	id="Command.ImportString2D" />ImportString2D</title>

	<para><command>ImportString2D(datasets,	string)</command></para>

	<para>Imports a two-dimensional dataset from the string
	given. This is similar to the <link
	linkend="Command.ImportFile2D">ImportFile2D</link> command,
	with the same dataset format within the string. This command,
	however, does not currently take any optional parameters. The
	various controlling parameters can be set within the
	string. See the <link
	linkend="Command.ImportFile2D">ImportFile2D</link> section for
	details.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.IsClosed" />IsClosed</title>

	<para><command>IsClosed()</command></para>

	<para>Returns a boolean value telling the caller whether the
	plotting window has been closed.
	</para>

	<para>Note: this command is only supported in the embedding
	interface.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.List" />List</title>

	<para><command>List(where='.')</command></para>

	<para>List the widgets which are contained within the widget
      with the path given, the type of widgets, and a brief
      description.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Load" />Load</title>

	<para><command>Load('filename.vsz')</command></para>

	<para>Loads the veusz script file given. The script file can
	be any Python code. The code is executed using the Veusz
	interpreter.</para>

	<para>Note: this command is only supported at the command line
	and not in a script. Scripts may use the python
	<command>execfile</command> function instead.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.MoveToPage" />MoveToPage</title>

	<para><command>MoveToPage(pagenum)</command></para>

	<para>Updates window to show the page number given of the
	document.</para>

	<para>Note: this command is only supported in the embedding
	interface or veusz_listen.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.ReloadData" />ReloadData</title>

	<para><command>ReloadData()</command></para>

	<para>Reload any datasets which have been linked to
	files.</para>

	<para>Returns: A tuple containing a list of the imported
	datasets and the number of conversions which failed for a
	dataset.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Rename" />Rename</title>

	<para><command>Remove('widgetpath', 'newname')</command></para>

	<para>Rename the widget at the path given to a new name. This
	command does not move widgets.  See <link
	linkend="Command.To">To</link> for a description of the path
	syntax. '.' can be used to select the current widget.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Remove" />Remove</title>

	<para><command>Remove('widgetpath')</command></para>

	<para>Remove the widget selected using the path. See <link
	linkend="Command.To">To</link> for a description of the path
	syntax.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.ResizeWindow" />ResizeWindow</title>

	<para><command>ResizeWindow(width, height)</command></para>

	<para>Resizes window to be width by height pixels.</para>

	<para>Note: this command is only supported in the embedding
	interface or veusz_listen.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Save" />Save</title>

	<para><command>Save('filename.vsz')</command></para>

	<para>Save the current document under the filename
	given.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Set" />Set</title>

	<para><command>Set('settingpath', val)</command></para>

	<para>Set the setting given by the path to the value given. If
	the type of <command>val</command> is incorrect, an
	<command>InvalidType</command> exception is thrown. The path
	to the setting is the optional path to the widget the setting
	is contained within, an optional subsetting specifier, and the
	setting itself.</para>

	<informalexample>
	  <programlisting>
Set('page1/graph1/x/min', -10.)
</programlisting>
	</informalexample>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetAntiAliasing" />SetAntiAliasing</title>

	<para><command>SetAntiAliasing(on)</command></para>

	<para>Enable or disable anti aliasing in the plot
	window, replotting the image.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetData" />SetData</title>

	<para><command>SetData(name, val, symerr=None, negerr=None,
      poserr=None)</command></para>

	<para>Set the dataset name with the values given. If None is
      given for an item, it will be left blank. val is the actual
      data, symerr are the symmetric errors, negerr and poserr and the
      getative and positive asymmetric errors. The data can be given
      as lists or numpys.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetDataExpression" />SetDataExpression</title>

	<para><command>SetDataExpression(name, val, symerr=None, negerr=None,
      poserr=None, linked=False, parametric=None)</command></para>

	<para>Create a new dataset based on the expressions given. The
	expressions are Python syntax expressions based on existing
	datasets.
</para>

	<para>If linked is True, the dataset will change as the
	datasets in the expressions change.</para>

	<para>Parametric can be set to a tuple of (minval, maxval,
	numitems). <command>t</command> in the expression will iterate
	from minval to maxval in numitems values.</para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetDataRange" />SetDataRange</title>

	<para><command>SetDataRange(name, numsteps, val, symerr=None,
	    negerr=None, poserr=None, linked=False)</command></para>

	<para>Set dataset to be a range of values with numsteps
	steps. val is tuple made up of (minimum value, maximum
	value). symerr, negerr and poserr are optional tuples for the
	error bars.</para>

	<para>If linked is True, the dataset can be saved in a
	document as a SetDataRange, otherwise it is expanded to the
	values which would make it up.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetData2D" />SetData2D</title>

	<para><command>SetData2D('name', val, xrange=(A,B),
	yrange=(C,D), xgrid=[1,2,3...],
	ygrid=[4,5,6...])</command></para>

	<para>Creates a two-dimensional dataset with the name
	given. val is either a two-dimensional numpy array, or is a
	list of lists, with each list in the list representing a
	row. Do not give xrange if xgrid is set and do not give yrange
	if ygrid is set, and vice versa.</para>

	<para>xrange and yrange are optional tuples giving the
	inclusive range of the X and Y coordinates of the data. xgrid
	and ygrid are optional lists, tuples or arrays which give the
	coordinates of the edges of the pixels. There should be one
	more item in each array than pixels.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetData2DExpression" />SetData2DExpression</title>
	
	<para><command>SetData2DExpression('name', expr, linked=False)</command></para>

	<para>Create a 2D dataset based on expressions.  name is the
        new dataset name expr is an expression which should return a
        2D array linked specifies whether to permanently link the
        dataset to the expressions.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetData2DExpressionXYZ"
	/>SetData2DExpressionXYZ</title>

	<para><command>SetData2DExpressionXYZ('name', 'xexpr',
	'yexpr', 'zexpr', linked=False)</command></para>

	<para>Create a 2D dataset based on three 1D expressions. The
	x, y expressions need to evaluate to a grid of x, y points,
	with the z expression as the 2D value at that point. Currently
	only linear fixed grids are supported. This function is
	intended to convert calculations or measurements at fixed
	points into a 2D dataset easily. Missing values are filled
	with NaN.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetData2DXYFunc"
	/>SetData2DXYFunc</title>

	<para><command>SetData2DXYFunc('name', xstep, ystep, 'expr',
	linked=False)</command></para>

	<para>Construct a 2D dataset using a mathematical expression
	of "x" and "y". The x values are specified as (min, max, step)
	in xstep as a tuple, the y values similarly. If linked remains
	as False, then a real 2D dataset is created, where values can
	be modified and the data are stored in the saved file.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetDataDateTime"
	/>SetDataDateTime</title>

	<para><command>SetDataDateTime('name', vals)</command></para>

	<para>Creates a datetime dataset of name given. vals is a list
	of Python datetime objects.</para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetDataText" />SetDataText</title>

	<para><command>SetDataText(name, val)</command></para>

	<para>Set the text dataset name with the values given.
	  <command>val</command> must be a type that can be converted into a
	  Python list.</para>

	<informalexample>
	  <programlisting>
SetDataText('mylabel', ['oranges', 'apples', 'pears', 'spam'])
</programlisting>
	</informalexample>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetToReference" />SetToReference</title>

	<para><command>SetToReference(setting, refval)</command></para>

	<para>Set setting to match other setting refval
	always..</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetUpdateInterval"
	/>SetUpdateInterval</title>

	<para><command>SetUpdateInterval(interval)</command></para>

	<para>Tells window to update every interval milliseconds at
	most. The value 0 disables updates until this function is
	called with a non-zero. The value -1 tells Veusz to update the
	window every time the document has changed. This will make
	things slow if repeated changes are made to the
	document. Disabling updates and using the ForceUpdate command
	will allow the user to control updates directly.</para>

	<para>Note: this command is only supported in the embedding
	interface or veusz_listen.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.SetVerbose" />SetVerbose</title>

	<para><command>SetVerbose(v=True)</command></para>

	<para>If <command>v</command> is <command>True</command>, then extra
	information is printed out by commands.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.StartSecondView"
	/>StartSecondView</title>

	<para><command>StartSecondView(name = 'window title')</command></para>

	<para>In the embedding interface, this method will open a new
	Embedding interface onto the same document, returning the
	object. This new window provides a second view onto the
	document. It can, for instance, show a different page to the
	primary view. name is a window title for the new
	window.</para>

	<para>Note: this command is only supported in the embedding
	interface.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.TagDatasets" />TagDatasets</title>

	<para><command>TagDatasets('tag', ['ds1', 'ds2'...])</command></para>

	<para>Adds the tag to the list of datasets given..</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.To" />To</title>

	<para><command>To('widgetpath')</command></para>

	<para>The To command takes a path to a widget and moves to
        that widget. For example, this may be "/", the root widget,
        "graph1", "/page1/graph1/x", "../x". The syntax is designed to
        mimic Unix paths for files. "/" represents the base widget
        (where the pages reside), and ".." represents the widget next
        up the tree.</para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Quit" />Quit</title>

	<para><command>Quit()</command></para>

	<para>Quits Veusz. This is only supported in
	veusz_listen.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.WaitForClose" />WaitForClose</title>

	<para><command>WaitForClose()</command></para>

	<para>Wait until the plotting window has been closed.
	</para>

	<para>Note: this command is only supported in the embedding
	interface.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title><anchor id="Command.Zoom" />Zoom</title>

	<para><command>Zoom(factor)</command></para>

	<para>Sets the plot zoom factor, relative to a 1:1
	scaling. factor can also be "width", "height" or "page", to zoom
	to the page width, height or page, respectively.</para>

	<para>This is only supported in embedded mode or
	veusz_listen.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Security</title>
      <para>With the 1.0 release of Veusz, input scripts and
      expressions are checked for possible security risks. Only a
      limited subset of Python functionality is allowed, or a dialog
      box is opened allowing the user to cancel the
      operation. Specifically you cannot import modules, get
      attributes of Python objects, access globals() or locals() or do
      any sort of file reading or manipulation. Basically anything
      which might break in Veusz or modify a system is not
      supported. In addition internal Veusz functions which can modify
      a system are also warned against, specifically Print(), Save()
      and Export().</para>

      <para>If you are running your own scripts and do not want to be
      bothered by these dialogs, you can run veusz with the
      <command>--unsafe-mode</command> option.</para>
    </section>

  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Using Veusz from other programs</title>

    <section>
      <title>Non-Qt Python programs</title>
      <para>Veusz supports being embedded within other Python
      programs. The calling program can open up any number of plot
      windows, and manipulate the graphs using the Veusz scripting
      commands, which are exposed as methods of graph objects.
      </para>

      <para>Using the embedding interface, a Python program can create
      multiple Veusz plot windows showing the same or different
      documents. The standard Veusz operations are supported with the
      addition of a few specific commands.</para>

      <para>The embedding interface runs Veusz in a second process,
      sending the commands over a pipe.</para>

      <para>Veusz must be installed in the PYTHONPATH for embedding to
      work. This can be done with the <command>setup.py</command>
      distutils script. An example embedding program is in
      <command>examples/embedexample.py</command>.</para>

      <para>An example Python program embedding Veusz is below:</para>
	<informalexample>
	  <programlisting>
import time
import numpy
import veusz.embed as veusz

g = veusz.Embedded('new window title')
g.To( g.Add('page') )
g.To( g.Add('graph') )
g.SetData('x', numpy.arange(20))
g.SetData('y', numpy.arange(20)**2)
g.Add('xy')
g.Zoom(0.5)

# wait 20 seconds
time.sleep(20)

win2 = veusz.Embedded('second window example')
win2.To( win2.Add('page') )
win2.To( win2.Add('graph') )
win2.Add('function', function='x**2')
win2.Set('x/label', 'An example axis \\emph{label}')

time.sleep(20)

g.Close()
</programlisting>
	</informalexample>

      <para>The supported commands are the same as in <link
      linkend="Commands">Commands</link>, with the addition of:
      Close, EnableToolbar, MoveToPage, ResizeWindow,
      SetUpdateInterval, StartSecondView and Zoom.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>PyQt4 programs</title>
      <para>There is no direct PyQt4 interface. The standard
      embedding interface should work, however.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Non Python programs</title>

      <para>Support for non Python programs is available in a limited
      form. External programs may execute the
      <command>veusz_listen</command> executable or
      <command>veusz_listen.py</command> Python module. Veusz will
      read its input from the standard input, and write output to
      standard output. This is a full Python execution environment,
      and supports all the scripting commands mentioned in <link
      linkend="Commands">Commands</link>, a <command>Quit()</command>
      command, the <command>EnableToolbar()</command> and the
      <command>Zoom(factor)</command> command listed above. Only one
      window is supported at once, but many
      <command>veusz_listen</command> programs may be started.</para>

      <para><command>veusz_listen</command> may be used from the shell
      command line by doing something like:</para>
	<informalexample>
	  <programlisting>
veusz_listen &lt; in.vsz
</programlisting>
      </informalexample>
      <para>where <command>in.vsz</command> contains:</para>
	<informalexample>
	  <programlisting>
To(Add('page') )
To(Add('graph') )
SetData('x', arange(20))
SetData('y', arange(20)**2)
Add('xy')
Zoom(0.5)
Export("foo.eps")
Quit()
</programlisting>
      </informalexample>

    <para>A program may interface with Veusz in this way by using the
    <command>popen</command> C Unix function, which allows a program
    to be started having control of its standard input and
    output. Veusz can then be controlled by writing commands to an
    input pipe.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>C, C++ and Fortran</title>

      <para>A callable library interface to Veusz is on my todo list
      for C, C++ and Fortran. Please tell me if you would be
      interested in this option.</para>

    </section>

  </chapter>
</book>
